this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hey this is Jeremy Jung for
software engineering radio today I'm
talking with vladimir cord coffee
Vladimir is the author of the book unit
testing principles practices and
patterns is a Microsoft MVP and he's the
author of many Pluralsight courses
including applying functional principles
in c-sharp and today we're going to be
talking about functional programming and
enterprise applications
Vladimir welcome to software engineering
radio thank you for having me the first
thing I want to talk about is sort of
what functional programming means to you
because it means different things to
different people
to you what are the core principles of
functional programming if I were to
describe functional programming in just
a couple of words I would say that
functional programming is programming
without hidden inputs and outputs and
that's basically it and what I mean by
hidden inputs and outputs is there are
several examples of those so the most
prevalent example of a hidden output is
immutability so let's say that you have
a method that takes in some integer and
then increments that integer by one what
it can do is it can return that
incremented integer back as the return
value but it can also mutate some global
state with that integer and by the way
by hidden I mean that this information
is not present in the method signature
and so it's not present in the method
arguments and it is not present in the
methods return value so in this example
when when you have this increment method
if it returns a value then it
communicates what it does pretty clearly
so it is honest about what it does but
if
instead mutates some global state then
this would be an example of a hidden
output because that output is not
present in the method signature and to
understand what this method does you
have to drill down to that method and to
see what what's actually going on
because you can this information is not
present in the in the signature itself
so that would be an example of a hidden
output a hidden input is similar to that
so instead of taking that integer as a
parameter as an argument
this method can also refer to some
global state some for example some
static property or field or it can refer
to some external service to request that
integer and then increment it and then
put it to some global state so that
would be an example of a hidden output
also reaching out to external systems
such as the database or AP is would be
that and also the simple date/time that
now would also be an example of an
hidden input because that input always
changes it basically refers to the
system's low level API your for example
windows api or linux api to get this
input value so that's another example of
each of a hidden input another example
of a hidden output would be something
like exceptions so exceptions are a
hidden output because when you throw an
exception and that exception is caught
somewhere upper the call stack this
exception also is not present in the
method signature and you basically
introduce another hidden pathway for
your program flow that is not present in
the method signature
so these are common examples of hidden
inputs and outputs and function
programming is about avoiding those
hidden inputs and outputs if your
mathematical function pure function
would be something that accepts a value
as an argument and returns a value and
doesn't do anything other than that
okay so let's sort of break down a few
of those so the first thing is hidden
outputs in terms of if you pass
something
to a function and the thing that you
pass in becomes changed then that in
effect is a hidden output because there
is no way of telling just from the
method signature whether that behavior
is possible correct yes and so you're
saying that the alternative to that is
to make sure that the function is pure
so that when you have something in if
you are going to make a change it would
not eat what you passed in but it would
be something that you're returning back
yes so instead of mutating the state of
some existing object what you need to do
instead in functional program is you
need to create a new object with the
required properties so instead of
mutating the object that is passed in
you need to create a new object with new
properties and return it back and with
example with a number increment that's
basically it because when you increment
the number by one and return it back
you're not changing the input parameter
because it's a constant you can't change
it what you do instead is you create
another number and return it back and
when we think about objects that we pass
in or we think about collections a lot
of times the objects and collections we
work with are mutable right like we can
have a list type in c-sharp for example
and we may want to add something to the
list or remove something to the list if
we are instead creating a new list every
time we want to change something what
are the performance implications of that
well yeah differently so there are
trade-offs a functional program and one
of the most common trade-offs to any
immutability is this trade-off of always
creating new objects instead of mutating
new ones and that's actually the reason
why object-oriented program has become
so so popular in the past because if you
know functional programming actually was
introduced before object-oriented
program but why didn't take off is
because computers back then
were not as powerful as now and so it
was very costly to do functional
programming with all those memory
allocations with all those new object
creation so it was very costly to do so
and what we had had instead is we
started to operate at the lower level of
our programmers and we started to think
in terms of memory allocations so but
now we're kind of getting back to the
roots and starting to do more of what we
did back then there are differently
trade-offs here and if your performance
requirements on for application are
strict then there are some restrictions
so there are some limitations and
probably you will not be able to
implement some functional programming
approaches but in most business line
applications that's not something you
need to worry about so if you write some
framework for example an asp.net
application application but the server
itself gastrula then you do need to
worry about that but in most enterprise
level applications you don't so
performance is not the biggest concern
the biggest concern is usually the
complexity and the uncontrollable growth
of complexity and what functional
programming allows you to do is it
allows you to reduce that complexity at
the expense of maybe and not as
performant code as you could have
otherwise so would you say that in the
average application that the developer
should default to making things
immutable is that a reasonable default
for most developers I would say so yes
if it is possible then you definitely
need to default to creating immutable
classes immutable objects by default it
is not always possible and one of the
limitations why is in object-oriented
languages it's pretty hard to create new
objects based on the existing objects so
for example if you take f-sharp there is
a really nice language feature where you
can take data structure or an object and
create a new object based on that
existing object with that
of new properties to that object so you
can say for example old object with some
property equals new value and some other
property equals other new value and what
it will do it will not mutate the
existing object but it will create a new
object with those two properties change
it then but all the old properties they
will remain the same and this is a
really nice feature that helps you to
default to immutability unfortunately in
object-oriented languages like C sharp
we don't have such features and so it's
not all this feasible to do so what what
I recommend you do instead is if you
have some value or a simple class you
can wrap it into a value object which is
immutable
but for all other classes such as
entities like for example a user or a
company that is usually something that
you need to mutate and that is an
example of an entity it has its own
inherit identity such classes usually
it's usually not feasible to make them
immutable but what you can do is you can
we keep them mutable but put as much
logic as possible to those immutable
value objects and this way you can keep
this separation between complexity and
immutability so your objects will be
either mutable or complex but not both
you keep this separation on between the
complexity and mutability because it is
when you combine the two you start to
have these problems with the ever
increasing complexity with unmanageable
complexity and you were referring to the
concept entities and value object but
you wanted yes and so what what is the
distinction between those two you were
saying that a value object should be
immutable and an entity could be mutable
like how do you decide which is which is
which yeah these two concepts are from
the main dreaming design but they are
actually applicable to any application
in which even if you don't follow I mean
during design principles it is handy to
refer to your objects in this way anyway
the main distinction between them is
that an entity is something that is
trackable by your application it has an
internal inherent identity an example I
often give is let's say you have a
dollar bill so you have money class and
this money represents a dollar bill so
this dollar bill would be a value object
in most systems because in most cases
you don't really care if you have the
exact same dollar bill as you had before
so let's say if you give someone a one
dollar bill and they give you back also
one dollar bill you don't care if it was
in the same piece of paper as before
because for you they are integer
interchangeable and that is one of the
most important properties of all your
objects they are interchangeable but
that also depends on the domain model so
on your context for example if you
create a system that tracks those dollar
bills dollar notes then in this case the
those bills and those pieces of paper
they become entities because you do care
about each individual piece of paper so
you for example you can have the number
on that dollar bill has the ID of your
entity and then you track where it goes
throughout its lifetime so it becomes an
entity because it starts to have its own
identity and you cannot exchange one
dollar bill for another one because you
do care about their history does this
mean that pretty much anything that's an
entity would also exist in some kind of
permanent store like a database yes
exactly that's because you as I said you
care about the history on that entity
and what it usually manifests in as you
need to persist that entity in the
database and then look after the changes
in this entity and you were kind of
referring to the fact that these
entities could act as wrappers to value
objects so I want to kind of give an
example of let's say I have a a
ride-sharing company and I'm keep
tract of my my fleet of vehicles so I
have cars that are driving around the
city and they're all reporting back to
me their position and each of my cars
has an ID which parts of my data would
be an entity and which part would be a
value object yeah that's a good example
of where you can apply this entity value
object separation so the car itself
would be an entity because you need to
track it that's the primary indication
that it is an entity it has an init ID
and the position itself would be a value
object because you can replace it with
another object with the same content and
two positions of the same type and
content they are interchangeable for you
so yeah that's a good example and so the
individual updates they would have the
ID of the vehicle and the actual
position that could be a value object
and as I'm receiving multiple updates
from each of my vehicles its reusing the
same ID and in my database I might want
to keep a history of you know all the
locations that my car went
so with those historical positions would
those be their own entity or what would
those be so the positions themselves
would not be their own entity in this
case what would be an entity is the
historical record so in this case you
wouldn't have the position itself as an
entity with an ID but you would still
have some let's say vehicle history
record or something like that as another
entity that would also contain the
position as a value object so you will
have this kind of nesting here where you
still have the same with your object but
the entity would be a different entity I
see and so the reason that we have the
value object is that it sort of tells
our system that this concept of a
location is identical whether it's in
the context of being an update I'm
getting from a vehicle versus
historical position they're really both
the same concept so I can use the same
value object for both yes exactly
it is much easier to reuse this position
with your object between these two
concepts and also another reason why you
wouldn't want to introduce a video
object for these two positions is
because it is much easier to keep
consistency in this way so let's say you
have other properties in your vehicle
other than the position itself so let's
say vehicle has a license plate and
let's say it has two numbers of its
license plate and it also has two
properties that display the position of
the vehicle so x-coordinate and
y-coordinate let's see why you would
want to introduce value objects it is to
reduce complexity because when you have
those four properties as just four
properties then the number of
permutations between them is higher than
it would if you group those properties
into separate video objects so if you
group the two properties that belong to
the license plate into value object and
you're also group the two coordinates
into the position value object then you
will have only two properties inside of
that vehicle and the number of
permutations between them is much lower
it's just two whereas the number of
permutations between the four objects is
going to be well much much much larger
much larger number right so that's a
good way to think of complexity of your
system when you reduce the number of
properties that you need to keep in mind
your software automatically becomes much
simpler because it becomes much easier
to keep the consistency because for
example when you accept a position what
you need to do is you need to just check
the correctness of that position on its
own without its connection to other
properties of the vehicle at the same
for the license plate you don't need to
validate that license plate against the
position coordinates so yeah the
validation becomes simpler and just
maintenance overall becomes much simpler
too and so it sounds like rather than
having a vehicle
date type for example and making that
object be responsible for it the
validations of a license plate and the
validations of the position information
instead you break out those concepts
into their own objects so that those
objects when you create them they
validate whether or not it's valid and
so as long as you can successfully
create one you pass it into the
constructor for the vehicle update
entity and you you know that they're
correct because they were already
validated before you pass them in yes
exactly and that is one of the benefits
of functional programming is that when
you keep your objects immutable your
value objects immutable you only need to
validate those objects once when you
create them after that you can be sure
that those objects remain in the
consistent in the correct state so you
don't need to validate them afterwards
do you find that in development code
wise is it easier to reason about what's
happening when you're creating these
objects and then creating the entity and
then passing these objects into the
entity versus having a larger
constructor or the entity well it
depends on the use case so usually what
I like to do is I like to do it
hierarchically so you first create a
lower-level objects such as as you said
value objects and then if you have some
other value object that consists of
those lower-level value objects you
create that value object and then you
pass that you kind of create that
structure where you go bottom-up from
the lower level objects to that higher
level objects and you create them
sequentially one by one and on the tab
at the top of that pyramid you have the
entity itself which you can create just
by passing those already validated value
objects into that entities constructor
and you don't need to do much else so
the entity itself becomes much simpler
to to maintain in these examples we've
been giving the value
objects they've been able to validate
themselves like for example to position
there's only a fixed set of numbers that
are valid for the position and so we
could validate that without talking to
an external store or database or
anything like that how about when you
have a case where to see if something is
valid you need to talk to an external
API or talk to a database like for
example if there was some kind of driver
registration or like a license that's
associated with the car and you needed
to talk to some kind of state API or
city information to find out if that car
update is valid where would that exist
in your application yeah so there is
kind of debate into where you should put
this logic I strongly recommend not
putting it inside your domain model
because your domain model shouldn't talk
to any external systems so you should
make that my model as functionally pure
as possible let me step back for a
second and describe what I mean by that
so what you want to do in your
application especially if you try to
adhere to functional programming you
don't actually want to make all your
code immutable because that's usually
impossible when you create an
application you do want that application
to mutate some state because otherwise
that application would be useless for
example if you create a user or if you
update the vehicle information you do
want that information to be eventually
updated so the vehicle records in the
database it should be updated and what
you need to strive for is the so-called
functional architecture and this
architecture is where you have some sort
of a sandwich between where you first
gather the information required for the
business operation then you delegate
that information so you pass that
information and delegate the work to the
domain model and then when the domain
lap model completes its work you persist
the results of that war
to the database and so what you can do
here is you can make your domain model
as purely functional as possible and
this way you kind of push the mutable
iterations to the edges of your system
to the edges of your business operation
because as I said you cannot escape
those immutable aberrations
altogether but you can kind of work
around them and with this approach with
this functional architecture what you
achieve is you achieve this separation
between the two important concerns so
the Des Moines model is responsible for
your domain logic and I like to call it
immutable core and the rest of your
system becomes mutable shell so it is a
dumb shell that is responsible for
communicating with external systems
primarily and so the two
responsibilities here are the main
modeling and orchestration and you don't
want to mix them together because when
mixed together they over complicate your
code you know you don't you don't want
to do that because the code becomes much
harder to maintain so yeah so this is
the functional architecture this kind of
sandwich were the beginning at the top
of your business operation it talks to
external systems then it passes control
to your domain model which is as purely
functional as possible and then at the
bottom all the decisions made by the
domain model and communicates it to
external systems including your database
in some cases the flow of your domain
logic itself depends on what kind of
response you get from external systems
so in your in your example and this
response would be whether or not this
vehicle with this number already exists
in the database and if it does you
cannot register a new vehicle with the
same number what you can do is you can
delegate some decisions to the
controller for which you have to reach
out to external systems such as the
database because the alternative to that
one and would be to delegate this
responsibility for communication with
the database to determine model itself
and this way you will keep the
controller simple but you will make
impure and that is in my opinion worse
option even though you kind of keep the
controller simple and you kind of keep
all the des moines logic inside the
domain model it's still not the best
approach because you want to separate
the domain model from this
responsibility of communicating with
external systems because when these two
responsibilities are combined together
that's when you start to have an over
complicated codebase if I understand
correctly
it sounds like anything that has to do
with external systems even if it's a
part of validation those calls should be
made at the outside layer like for
example in your application controller
or in an object that's receiving
messages from an external system and
that is where you would make the call to
check in your database to see if for
example if this was an ID that already
existed or if you know we needed to talk
to some city's registration system to
see if this vehicle is licensed we would
do all of that outside of the value
objects we would do that more in our
controller or in some area outside of
all of the internal domain objects yes
that's correct
so you're the my model you cannot
delegate these responsibility of
maintaining consistency that spans
across the whole database so you only
need to delegate your domain model the
consistency requires that spam the
objects themselves so ideally it should
stay within a single entity or in the my
dream design terms and aggregate and
aggregate is a group of related entities
if your consistency requirement spans
more than one aggregate or one entity
then yes it usually should be attributed
to the controller itself so and they
check for uniqueness let's say user
email uniqueness or vehicle number
uniqueness that's an example of such a
validation yes let's say you have a
value object that is a vehicle and the
for we checked with the database we
didn't know if it was a valid new
vehicle or not because we didn't know if
it was already existing or if it's truly
new and at the controller we make a
request to the database and we find out
that this vehicle doesn't already exist
yet so it's a valid request to create a
new vehicle would we then need to create
a new type that says like this is a
valid vehicle creation request because
if we hadn't done that check yet then we
wouldn't actually know if it was valid
yet I don't know if that makes sense
yeah it does so what you're talking
about is you want to have let's say an
idempotent request and they had to put
either create a new vehicle or update an
existing one if it already exists
correct sure yeah yeah I wouldn't create
a new request for that so uhm if it is a
requirement if it is a business
requirement to do that in one go which
it sounds like it is here then I would
just attribute this logic to their
controller so first Jack if this vehicle
with this IDE exists and then go from
there either update its position using
this value object or create a new
vehicle using the same value object so
in this case you will work with the same
position value object anyway because you
will use it for creation and for update
of the vehicle position and so it's just
a matter of what to do next when you see
if the vehicle exists or not and so
after we've completed this validation
and we created our value object then
when we persist it to our database that
would also be in the controller is that
correct yes so the creation of the
vehicle that part would be the domain
logic part so if we are talking about
the sandwich architecture again the
functional architecture then the top
part of the sandwich would be reaching
out the database to see if the vehicle
exists at the middle part
model part would be the creation of a
new vehicle or the update of the
existing vehicle and then the bottom
part would be saving that vehicle to the
database yes hiring a software engineer
then we recommend working with g 2i g 2i
is the most effective way to discover
talented and pre-vetted engineers for
every project g2 I vets their talent
pool through technical interviews and
various code challenges which are graded
by actual engineers saving you time and
guaranteeing you top quality through
their transparent grading they
specialize in react react native and
nodejs interested in learning more and
go to g2 IC o----
[Music]
and I want to kind of step back to at
the start of our conversation you were
talking about hidden inputs and hidden
outputs and one of the things that you
were talking about as being a hidden
output is the exception for example like
if there's a an error that occurs you
may not know that an exception is
something that can return walk us
through like why that's an issue or or
if that is an issue the issue here is
not the exception per se but how you use
those exceptions so if you use those
exemptions for validation then it does
become an issue I would I like to say
with regards to exceptions is that
exceptions are for exceptional
situations only and what I mean by that
is situations that you did not expect to
happen in your application a validation
is by definition an expected Association
because you do expect your clients or
your users to enter incorrect values or
send you interact data and so on and so
when you validate that data you do
expect it to be sometimes at least to be
incorrect and so what you can do is you
can for example validate that date and
then if it is incorrect you can throw an
exception saying that this data is
incorrect but it has the drawback of
this hidden output that I mentioned
earlier where you create another path in
the program flow that is not present in
the method signature so let's say if you
have a method a void method that accepts
some data and then throws an exemption
you cannot be sure what it does so you
cannot be sure how you react to these
exceptions because it could be in that
these exceptions are caught and the
method and that now call this validate
method but it could also be several
layers upper the call stack and so it
becomes much harder to debug this
application and much harder to
understand what it does
with something like a result type what
you could do is you can explicitly
return the result of the validation from
that method and this way you will make
the signature honest so an honest
signature is something I like to also
refer to a purely a purely functional
method would have an honest signature
because it will tell you explicitly what
it does what it what inputs it has and
what outputs it produces the drawback
with the result type is that you often
need to write more code because without
them you can basically just make several
validations call several validate
methods and then if something is wrong
you will catch an exception in the catch
part of your application but with result
you have to process each output
separately so you have the first result
which you need to process at the second
one and so on and also another issue
here is that it becomes at least in
object-oriented programming languages
like C sharp it becomes simpler to omit
that result because there's nothing
preventing you to just forget about it
and ignore it and yeah that that could
be an issue and that is one of the
trade-offs of this functional
programming approach but again I think
the benefits of this approach over
weight the costs because you're becoming
much more explicit in the values those
methods return and it is much more
maintainable in the long run and by the
way this issue with the ignore able
outputs it is only present in all P
languages like C sharp for example if
you take F sharp you cannot just ignore
an output which is none which is
non-void or unit in F sharp terms you
have to pipe it into special function
ignore so you can always see that you
are ignoring something because you are
seeing that the return value is piped
into that ignore method for those who
aren't familiar with result types can
you kind of give a brief explanation
but they're a result is an explicit
representation of some operation so
let's say when you perform some
operation let's say you're trying to
save something in an external system
let's say that you want to update your
profile on Facebook and you are using a
Facebook API for that and so you're you
you're doing some API calls to the
Facebook API and this iteration
obviously may fail and one of the ways
to deal with that failure is as I said
before is to use exceptions but that's
not the best way to deal with that
because I it is not often obvious where
exactly you process those failures a
better way would be to catch those
potential exemptions from that API at
the lowest level possible and then wrap
them into an explicit structure such as
a result class and the result class is a
simple structure that tells you whether
or not this operation succeeded so it
has such fields as is it a failure or is
it a success and if the operation
numbers supposed to return a value then
you can also make this result class
generic and if it is successful it can
also contain a value that will contain
the result of the operation the benefit
of using the result type is that your
function signatures they become very
explicit in telling you that this call
that you're gonna make it could succeed
or it could fail and this result type is
going to tell you whether it succeeds or
failed and and that way you know the
right code to account for both cases
exactly yes one of the things about
exceptions is that when an exception
occurs there's a lot of information
that's kind of embedded with it
generally a full stack trace for example
whereas with a result type you may not
have any additional information on why
something failed how do you deal with
that or are there cases where you would
say it does make sense to use an
exception instead yeah I'm not saying
that you shouldn't use exceptions at all
because there are use cases for them and
one of those use cases is well actually
the only use case is
where you have an a situation that you
cannot you don't know how to deal with
and for example if that Facebook API
returns an error that you didn't expect
so let's say that when you wrote this
software you expected some set of errors
from the Facebook let's say then the
user doesn't exist but if it returns
some other error some obscure error you
don't necessarily know how to deal with
that error and in this case because you
don't know how to deal with that it is
preferable to throw an exception this
would be an example of an unexpected
situation for which exceptions are
preferable because exceptions represent
unexpected situations in code and you
shouldn't catch them
you should only change them at the
topmost level of your call stack and the
only way you should react to them is to
just lock what exactly happened and then
basically crash the application or if
it's some background process you need to
just restart all over again because
otherwise if you're if you're trying to
continue working after this exemption
took place what you can run into as you
can run into an inconsistent state where
your program entered some state where
it's kind of still working but it may
become inconsistent and even save some
data into the database where it will
become much harder to deal with because
you want to avoid that inconsistency as
much as possible and as soon as that
inconsistency takes place you want to
stop everything basically crash your
application and that would be the only
use case for exceptions and so in this
case you do still have the call stack
which you can then log somewhere and
deal somewhere somehow later but if it
is unexpected situations let's say that
the Facebook API returned that this user
doesn't exist then you do know how to
deal with that and you basically don't
need the exception
because you can just process these error
from the Facebook turn it into a result
object and then return back to the polar
and the color then can in turn show some
friendly error message to the user so so
basically when you're working with
external API it's like the Facebook API
you may make a HTTP request and maybe it
times out and the HTTP library that's
built into c-sharp I believe it with
their own exception and what you're
saying is that you would know ahead of
time that I expect that there may be
times where my request times out or it
fails I'm going to catch this exception
and then I'm going to return a result
type that kind of explains what the
failure was rather than just throwing
that exception and catching it somewhere
else yes but that depends on whether or
not you know how to deal with that even
if you expect some time out yeah let's
say that the Facebook API calls to that
API may timeout from time to time so you
need to see whether or not you can deal
with those errors because if you cannot
then even if you expect those situations
to happen you basically cannot do
anything about them and so you need to
throw an exception anyway and that could
be because let's say the Facebook API is
essential for this operation and you
cannot proceed without a response from
Facebook but if it is not essential
let's say if a user updates its profile
and you want to update its Facebook
profile as well simultaneously but if
you cannot do that then still fine you
can proceed further so in this case you
can see that this Facebook call was a
failure but you know that it is not
essential for this business separation
and you can just ignore that result and
move on and another example let's say
you write an ORM such as entity
framework and in this rme the lack of
connection to the database would be an
exceptional situation because you cannot
do anything about that and you don't
know how the user of your library will
act to that exception and so in this
case because you as a library writer you
do not know how to deal with that
exemption you also need to throw an
exception and then the library user such
as yourself or myself we can decide
whether or not this operation was
essential for us and whether or not we
can proceed with that exception or not
so let's say that when you're trying to
save something to the database it is
preferable to do that say for example
when you try to log something into the
database so it is preferable that the
log is successful but if it's not then
not a big deal and so in this case you
also need to catch that exception that
the library throws and then transform it
into a result class and then process it
up or at the call stack but if it is
essential for your application let's say
you're saving not a log entry but the
user itself then even if you know that
this URL can throw an exception you
cannot do anything about that and so you
shouldn't process that exception you
should basically allow it to pop up to
the upper layers where it will be locked
and your application will crash another
thing that you sometimes talk about in
the context of functional programming is
this idea of how object oriented
languages they usually have a a null
concept where instead of returning the
object you expect you return a null and
that could be because you can find the
element it could be any number of
reasons what are the drawbacks of
returning a null yeah it's a common one
billion dollar mistake and that all
object-oriented programming language is
half and them and that is the problem
with Mouse is that they make all your
code dishonest because what what they do
with your code let's say and that you
return a user from some method and that
user is a class so in c-sharp all
classes are not able so that you can
return not an object of that class but a
null and that would be a valid program
from the compiler perspective
the problem with that is that you cannot
differentiate between malleable user and
unknowable users and where you can see a
method that returns that user what it
actually does it returns a special class
which you can call user or now because
it may be either a user or now and so
when you want an unallowable user you
there's no way for you to do that
because all as I said all classes are
not able by default and yeah that's the
problem because that introduces another
hidden output that you cannot see just
by looking at the method signature one
of the things that you've done as a way
to kind of push back against that is
this concept of the maybe or an optional
type could you explain what those are
and how they're used I think what I did
in this course yeah then try to remember
it was several years ago yeah so what
you can do instead is there is a good
tool it's called fatty null guard that
you can use to basically inject null
checks in all your methods and
properties and what it will do is it
will check all input arguments for nulls
for you and also it will check output
return values for nulls as well and it's
a very good tool I try to use it in as
many of my project as possible but it's
not always possible let's say that and
what it does is it helps you to
approximate your code to this world
where nulls do not exist so if you try
to return a null where your method
returns a user your method will
automatically throw an exception because
of these automatic checks for nulls and
to avoid that you will need to use a
maybe or an option at an f-sharp so
maybe as a special struct that you can
use to explicitly tell the clients of
your code which parts of your inputs or
outputs can be now and because it is
maybe it itself cannot turn into an out
because it is struct and structs in
c-sharp are not knowable and it becomes
so
nice trick to avoid these null problems
because if you want to make your return
really user nullable you have to wrap it
with a maybe of user and you cannot do
that otherwise because if you try to
return null without that maybe your
method will throw an exception but if
you do use a maybe then you are now will
be automatically transformed into an
instance of that maybe a type and your
code will proceed the validation here is
not as strict as in functional
programming languages because these
issue with the null it will not be
caught at the compile time but still
it's close enough because even though
the compiler will see this code as valid
I mean the code where you return a user
but return null instead but it will
still feel at runtime so you'll have
sort of close to functional grantees
here as well sounds like it's similar to
the result type in the sense that with
the result type we were saying we would
wrap an object in a result and what that
would do to the method signature is it
would say that this function you're
gonna call it could succeed or it could
fail and similarly this may be type it
sounds like it's wrapping your object
it's wrapping your response and telling
you that your response could have
something in it or it could have nothing
in it and it's making it explicit as a
part of the return type yes exactly so
the the main be type and it gives you
the same benefits of the result type so
it makes the method explicit but in
addition to that if you use at this
party
now guard library it also gives you some
guarantees some runtime guarantees that
you will not actually have a null where
you return none may be user so if you
return just user then you have this
guarantee that it will actually be none
now instance because if you try to
return now then the application will
throw an exception something that
c-sharp added recently in c-sharp a is
it
non nullable reference types so it has a
compile type check to see if you could
possibly be using something that's null
is that a good substitute for this maybe
type or kind of what are your thoughts
on that feature
it's nice moving to the right direction
but I don't think that it is a good
enough substitute because those checks
will only give you compile warnings so
they are not compile errors but that's
not a big issue because you can turn
those foreigners into errors by setting
up a couple of things in Visual Studio
the main issue is that it doesn't catch
all the situations where you may have
nulls and so you still may have some
issues with mouse even though c-sharp 8
will tell you that everything is fine so
that's basically my concern with that
that it's not as strict as they may be
type it kind of gives you some
protection but there are some cases it
doesn't catch so it may give you this
false sense of security
yes exactly another thing that you bring
up in some of your courses is that when
data is coming in from an outside source
like let's say you have a API and
somebody sends you data via JSON or you
get data via a message queue you tend to
create a separate DTO a data transfer
object rather than use the entities or
the value types that you've created
internally why do you make the decision
to do that that's a very important thing
to do in my opinion because you need to
maintain the separation between data
contracts and your domain model and this
is important because if you are using
the same domain classes and as as these
input data structures then you may fall
into several problems so let's say that
you you have a controller that is
responsible for user creation
and one way to represent that data that
clients send you when they try to
register a new user now one way to do
that would be to use the same user
domain objects object as you have in the
domain model so let's say that it has
username a password and maybe some other
properties that map want to want to the
properties that the client sent you the
issue here the first issue here is the
security hole potential security hole
because you may introduce some
properties in the future to your domain
class that you don't want the client to
set so let's say that you introduce a
flag saying that this user is an admin
let's say it's a boolean is admin flag
and if you introduce it to your domain
model then it becomes a potential
security problem because now your
clients can send in this flag as well
and it will be deserialized into that
domain model and if you save it as ASM
to the database then it will basically
create another admin your system without
knowing that and so that's one another
problem here is that when you use your
domain classes like that you are setting
those domain classes in stone so to
speak because you often need to maintain
backward compatibility but with the
clients and what it means is you cannot
refactor those classes as often as you
may need so let's say that for example
your user has a name property and you
want to split it into first-name and
lastname but because you want to
maintain backward compatibility you
cannot just do that because the old
clients of your application will break
because they will not know that split
they will not know about it and they
will continue to send it you just one
name and in this case it becomes
problematic because now you have to
maintain sort of the old name property
but you also need to add the first name
and the last name and then count somehow
currently between the two maybe not
transform name into first and last name
using some rules and you don't want to
do that instead what you need to do is
you need to have
a separate layer of data contracts Duty
all data transfer objects where you have
as many versions of those data contracts
as you as you want so if you decide to
split the name in the first and last
names you don't need to modify the old
DT or you can create a new endpoint that
accepts in you DTO
version two let's say that we'll have
the first and the last name and then you
will do the conversion between these two
endpoints so the first endpoint this
still has the first version of the DTO
you can do the conversion between your
domain model and the old data structure
there and so in this way you are free to
modify to refactor your domain model
without looking back to how it makes
incompatible or backward compatible
changes for your clients and so you sort
of decouple that data contract from your
internal domain model you want the
internal that my model to move as fast
as you want so you want to be able to
refactor it but you want to keep the
data contracts backward compatible it's
almost like the difference between when
you have a class you have a public
interface and then you have the private
implementation and when you use data
transfer objects you expose an interface
that you want to keep the same but you
want to be able to modify how that's
handled internally in your system and so
having these DT o--'s it makes sure that
you can make as many changes as you want
internally in your system without
affecting what your API looks like to
the outside yes exactly it's it's a good
technology yes the one thing I can think
about as far as DT OS and converting
them to internal domain objects one of
the things about that so it sounds like
you could potentially have a lot of
conversion code how should you sort of
plan for that and where should that
exist in your application my view has
evolved since that course I think what I
did is I created extension methods on
top of result and it's still a good way
to do that let's say that when you
create a user you
to validate his first last name let's
say an email and let's say a couple of
other properties and what you can end up
with is a lot of code that does
validation so you are creating a value
object first and then you need to make
sure that the user with the same email
doesn't exist in the database and then
you need to create another with your
object and validate it so it creates a
lot of if-else statements and that
clutter your code base what you can do
instead is you can follow the so-called
railway oriented approach which was
introduced by Scott flushing and so what
I did is I basically adopted this
approach from F sharp to C sharp and you
can introduce extension methods that
will drastically simplify all those if
statements it will help you to reduce
the number of line codes by a factor of
three and without losing any readability
another way to do that and the way that
I prefer now is as I said you can still
do that and for simple validations it's
still a good approach but there is a
nice way of dealing with validation in
asp.net and that is validation
attributes and what I did in that course
I said that well validation attributes
is nice but they kind of don't play well
with value objects and so if you want to
really adhere to the meandering design
principles or functional principles then
you need to switch from those
annotations to this Railway oriented
approach but you actually can combine
the two so you can combine the approach
with annotations and still have this
validation logic in video objects so one
of the biggest disadvantages of having
those validations in annotations is that
you are duplicating that validation so
you want to keep those validation rules
inside your domain model because it is
part of your domain model it is
essential part of it but if when you put
let's say regular expression of
validation attributes on top of your
DDoS you are duplicating though
rules between the two parts of your
system so now you have a value object
with the same rules and and also that
same rule exists in the data annotations
so to combine the two you can actually
create your own custom annotations that
would delegate those checks to the value
objects but still would work exactly the
same way as the regular annotation
attributes meaning that you can
declaratively put them on top of your
DTO properties and they will work very
well so you will still reduce the number
of validation coatless lines drastically
but you will still keep this nice
declarative approach that you had with
annotations and I have a blog post on my
website we can link it in show notes
where I show this approaching detail
just to make sure I understand correctly
so what you're describing is in asp.net
when you have a model for the DTO you
can put annotations on it you can have
your property and above the property you
could say something like the max length
is 50 so this person's name can't be
more than 50 and what asp.net is able to
do is if you were to create a form and
you used that property in the form if
somebody typed in a name and they put in
80 characters asp.net using that
annotation would be able to
automatically create an error and you
would be able to put that next to the
field and I think what you're saying
that you can do is that you can keep
those sort of validation rules inside
the domain objects that you create our I
think you called them the the value
object and you're able to still write an
annotation that just refers to the
validation that exists in your value
object rather than using the built-in
data annotations yes yes exactly and
that's a nice way to combine the two
because it sort of combines the best of
the two worlds you still have your
validation rules in one place
what's your approach to when you have a
code base that has exceptions and it
passes back Knolls the calls to the
database are sort of mixed in with the
objects like how do you start that
process of bringing in more functional
concepts or just bringing in more
concepts that are easier to follow and
to understand yeah that's a great
question and yeah it's a tough one it
depends a lot on the specifics of that
project on specifics of the team and
management it's one thing if this
project doesn't evolve much and it's
just some project in the maintenance
mode where you don't need to introduce a
lot of new features in this case I
actually don't recommend that you do
much because it all most likely will not
pay off in the long run but if it is a
project that is actively developed then
it's a different story and in this case
you need to come up with some
refactoring approach some refactoring
strategy there I couple of approaches
here in the mentoring design for example
Eric Evans wrote a great piece where he
talked about so this approach that
involves bubble contexts and so a bubble
context is something that you create
inside a legacy code base that adheres
to all the good principles so you have a
nice separation between the main logic
and the orchestration and your domain
logic is ideally purely functional and
because you you cannot refactor the
whole application at once and I actually
don't recommend that you rewrite your
application either because it's it's not
a good idea in most cases you still want
to start somewhere and or you can start
is by creating these bubble context now
let's say that you have some new feature
or you need to modify an existing
feature and this feature is somewhat not
too connected to the other system and so
you can start to isolate these
functionality into the
context and surround that bubble context
with an anti-corruption layer and that
anti-corruption layer it's basically a
repository that converts you're good and
clean the main model into the database
with this messy legacy structure and
converts back into your nice and clean
domain model and what you can do is you
can start expanding that bubble context
you can gain territory more and more
with new features with new refactorings
and eventually what you want to do is
come to this point where your bubble
context becomes the main part of your
application and it's the legacy part
that is surrounded by the
anti-corruption layer this pattern is
also called a strangler pattern where
you strangle this legacy part and cut
off slices of functionality from that
part and transform it and refactor them
into your bubble context you need to
first define the building blocks of your
domain model and those building blocks
are usually video objects so the easiest
to create classes in your application
let's say as simple as an email with
your object or as simple as a customer
name with your object and so when you do
that you can put the main logic that
relates to those email and customer
names to those video objects start using
these video objects from the rest of
your system and then start from there so
you can build a hierarchy of value
objects so let's say that you have
another value object that consists of
those smaller building blocks smaller
value objects so you do that and then as
I said previously you can proceed to
your entities and refactor that entity
so instead of separate properties on the
entity you can start to have properties
defined as video objects and so you are
attributing more and more logic from
that entity to those value objects and
the entity itself becomes simpler and
then from that level you step even
further and push the domain logic
down from
controllers to those entities because
what you usually have in such legacy
systems is the anemic domain model where
your mind logic is separated from the
domain data so data is separated from
the logic and that we can talk about it
a bit too but the the main drawback in
this system is that it's hard to
maintain encapsulation hard to maintain
consistency inside the domain data
because it's separated from the logic
that works upon that data and the logic
itself is usually located in something
like services and so you can push that
logic from services down to entities and
so what do what you have it's sort of a
cascade of logic that you push further
and further down and the more down you
can push it the better because the
easier it will be to work with and the
problem with the anemic domain model is
that well there is actually a nice guy
commentary between anemic domain models
and functional programming because I
need my model is it's about separating
data from functions or from operations
that work upon the data but functional
programming is kind of the same so it's
also about separating data from
operations that work upon the data the
big difference between the two is that
in functional programming that data is
immutable and it is a big deal because
it's impossible to corrupt immutable
data so it's basically impossible to
corrupt something that you cannot change
but I need make the mind Mouse although
they exhibit similar properties to the
functional approach the biggest
difference is that it is mutable that
data inside the main models is mutable
and you can never know who mutates that
data and how they do that and so it
becomes impossible to enforce
restrictions on everyone whom you taste
that data with with such environment
given all the things we've talked about
if people want to kind of see an example
of a lot of these things in action are
there any code bases that they can take
a look at that are open source or any
good examples that you can point them to
if we are talking about c-sharp then I
would recommend my pyrrole site or
school
applying functional principles in
c-sharp or something like that I
actually have trial code for pure all
sides so if you want just reach out to
me we can put my email address so they
will give you I think it's 30 days and
limited access to plural sides so you
can watch all my courses and more and
during that time also if we're talking
f-sharp I would highly recommend Scott
washings books on this topic so he has
great sites called
f-sharp for fun and profit and it has a
section with books in it where one of
the books is basically the connection of
the articles from the site itself but
the other book is about demoing trimming
design combined with the functional
approach and it's really great book and
it explains how to do the Mayan dreaming
design in a functional programming
language like F sharp and where should
people go if they want to see more about
what you're working on and follow you
the best place is to go to my website
it's called enterprise craftsmanship
calm and yeah you will find all the
things that cool vladimir thank you so
much for coming on the show thank you
for having me this has been Jeremy Jung
for software engineering radio thanks
for listening thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
that will reach us on LinkedIn Facebook
Twitter or through our slack channel at
SC radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
se radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening
you